<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A looking-glasse for the vvell-affected in the city of London. Wherein they may behold those dangers and miseries which are ready to fall upon them if they do not speedily make a firm combination against the common enemy.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88535</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L3033</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E460_26</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205130</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864568</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864568</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116799</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88535)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116799)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 73:E460[26])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A looking-glasse for the vvell-affected in the city of London. Wherein they may behold those dangers and miseries which are ready to fall upon them if they do not speedily make a firm combination against the common enemy.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 12p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeer 1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "August ye 23th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>London (England) --  Defenses --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116799:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:116799:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> A Looking-Glaſſe FOR THE VVELL-AFFECTED in the City of LONDON.</p>
            <p>WHEREIN They may behold thoſe dangers and miſeries which are ready to fall upon them if they do not ſpeedily make a firm Combination againſt the Common Enemy.</p>
            <p>Printed in the yeer 1648.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:116799:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:116799:2"/>
            <head>An Admonition.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>NOw dangers us aſſail,</l>
               <l>And troubles us ſurround;</l>
               <l>Its time for us t'be friends,</l>
               <l>For fear our foes get ground.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Religion's now at ſtake,</l>
               <l>Our Lives our Liberties,</l>
               <l>Wherefore let's draw our ſwords,</l>
               <l>And joyn our Companies.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Let all our quarrels ſleep,</l>
               <l>Our Church diſſenſions flee:</l>
               <l>Lets joyn together in one,</l>
               <l>Live, love, and brethren be.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Let's wreſt theſe ſwords and ſpears</l>
               <l>Out of our Enemies, hands:</l>
               <l>Let's ſeize their Ordnance,</l>
               <l>And rout their ſwearing Bands.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That Legacy which we</l>
               <l>From our fore fathers have,</l>
               <l>Before wee'l loſe it thus</l>
               <l>Our bed ſhall be a grave.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Though Presbyterians,</l>
               <l>And Independents jar;</l>
               <l>Theſe know their miſery,</l>
               <l>Wee'l never fall to war.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:116799:3"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:116799:3"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear fellow Citizens,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Angerouſly are we diſtracted by the Common Enemy abroad, but more dangerouſly by the Common enemy at home, I meane our diſſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, diviſions, and Diſcontents. They are the battering Rams, wherewith the ſtrongeſt walls of our ſafety, love, affection, and unity are ſhattered and broken in pieces. The Artillery, which in time will Levell the Higheſt Turrets in our Common-wealth. The Powder-plot (which if not prevented by your cloſe ſarrying together) will blow up this, and all ſucceeding Parliaments; There is no way to undoe us, but by our own procurement: we cannot fall into our Enemies Traps and Pitfalls, unleſſe we be artificially miſerable<hi>:</hi> Our ſafety is impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, unleſſe we give the hand to our enemies, teare our Colours, march, and receive pay under our adverſaries ſtandards. Our owne Diviſions in Parliament, City, Kingdome, and Army, may reduce us to a confuſed heape. Our heart-burnings may cauſe our unbred, unborne, our unthought of Poſterities, to have heart-akings, when they ſhall weare yokes of iron, be whipped with laſhes of ſlavery, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted by the hand of Monarchicall, and Princely Tyranny<hi>:</hi> what danger by reaſon of your frivolous and needleſſe Diſcontents, may, and are ready to charge you? reade &amp; peruſe, it may be here you may finde them<hi>:</hi> what may be the beſt and moſt probable wayes for your ſafety, reade here, and if you pleaſe, you may uſe them. The ſafety both of you and yours is now concerned: it is within the ſpheare of your power, either to vanquiſh your enemies, or by fore-ſlowing reliefe and aſſiſtance to the Parl. and to your other freinds and allyes to enſlave and begger your whole poſterity. Did not a certaine foreſight of your Imminent ruine upon your neglectings and ſlighting the Parliament, and your honourable Gen. compell me to perſwade an accord, union, and ſweet Compliance. I had never publiſhed ſuch an Exhortation, but ſeeing the unbridled and Tempeſtuous fury of our old, once dead, but now revived enemy will not be aſſwaged, or be calmed, without either bringing us, or, being brought themſelves into a periſhing and forelorne Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: I thought it not altogether inconvenient, if I induced you to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:116799:4"/> recollect all the dangers, which may hazard the ruine of your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, your Lives, and your Liberties. Never were our lives more aymed at then now, by the Abners and Amaziahs of our daies, who make the murdering of us, but playing at the worſt, or looking one another in the face. Never could a more bloody, mercileſſe, and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous Enemy have oppoſed us, who will either ruine us, or be ru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ined themſelves, either their blood muſt be ſpilt or ours, their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates forfeited or ours, their or our poſterities beggered and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne to all Eternity. If we in this time of imminent danger, and greateſt extremity, ſhould ſtart aſide and detract a joynt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyance with our Grandees of State, and Militarie affaires; if we ſhould withdraw our aſſiſtance from our old Companions, and fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes in Armes, repoſing confidence in the glozing ſpeeches of a Butchering party: This favour deare Countrymen and fellow Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, you may expect from the Polyphemuſes of our times, to be the laſt that ſhall be devoured. Never were any ſo woed, Courted, and when they prevailed not, threatned, becauſe we would not ſell our birthright for a meſs of pottage, renounce our right bequeathed to a Legacy, full dearly bought with the blood of many of our noble An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors. How do vaſſalage and ſlavery threaten to baniſh Liberty, &amp; Lord it over us, when the P. of <hi>Wales</hi> is landed with a power of mercenary Walloones, a hotchpot of lewd forraigners, all Papiſts, and <hi>Venetian</hi> Adventurers: meerely like the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Allyes, the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians,</hi> whoſe only pay muſt be the plunder and pillage of whole Cities &amp; Counties? Will not theſe be to you in time, what the guard of <hi>Switzers</hi> are, and have been to the tumultuous Pariſiens? Will they in time be any more favourable to your City, then the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> garriſon to the poor <hi>Neapolitans?</hi> Will not theſe prove Lord Danes to your houſes, wives, &amp; Daughters? the ſweat of your browes ſhall be in vaine poured forth, for the maintenance of idle and Drone Bee foraigners, when theſe miſeries have taken you priſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and enchained you, it will be bitter to your remembrance, that ever you conteſted and daggered together, whether <hi>Presbytery,</hi> or <hi>Independency</hi> ſhall obtaine the Superiority. Our fortunes too, muſt be the object of men of fortune, <hi>Scotiſh, Iriſh, Engliſh, French, Walloones,</hi> all Rebells, or diſaffected perſons to our ſtate, though well-affected to our lands and goods, muſt (if poſſible by armed violence) be made Joyntenants of our Inheritances. Theſe Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oticke
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:116799:4"/> Mermidons, muſt be enriched with our Poſſeſſions by Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from the King, becauſe they did overthrow our great Charter, which they are to hold in pure villenage; for where the authority of a King is, there is power, and who may ſay unto him, what doeſt thou? Our Religion and glorious profeſſion of the truth, is endangered to ſuffer ſhipwrack, openly ſcandalized by the Gyants of our daies, who would make war with the Almighty, were not the Thunderbolts of Gods vengeance ready to ſtrike their ſoules out of their bodies, and death armed with a <hi>Capias ad reſpondendum</hi> before the great Judges tribunall of Heaven and Earth. How will the Chriſtall cleareneſſe of our Proteſtant Profeſſion be obfuſcated and fowly beſlimed by the frogges of the great river <hi>Euphrates,</hi> the Prelates and the Prelaticall Clergy, thoſe Locuſts of the bottomleſſe pit, who have cropped our harveſt of a glorious reformation, for many years, even in the Blade? theſe will recall your old ſtout behaviour, and deportment againſt them, and their Terreſtriall, nay rather their Celeſtiall god, the book of Common Prayer, that old divell, which hath ſo long bewitched and deluded the world, not under the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious garbe of a Munkes Coat, but of a Saints Doublet.</p>
            <p>The Papiſts too will not only riſe up in judgment againſt you, but aggravate your Condemnation: Theſe have underpropped the Divels Cauſe, with foreigne Contributions, with foreigne and Domeſtick armes, and with Domeſtick Contributions. My judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment apprehends what thoughts theſe kinde hearted Papiſts ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized in their fancies, not the reenthronizing the K. in his temporall regailty, but the reinſtalling of the Pope into his antiquated ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Hierarchie. Will <hi>Henretta Maria</hi> be content we ſhould enjoy our Religion in its purity, and undefiled? Will ſhe be deprived of the priviledge to be accounted the ſecond Saint in the Popes Calen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar, reſting ſatisfied with the brand of a Traytour in the Parlia. Diurnall? Will her Crew of <hi>Babilonians</hi> ſupercede the attempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our ruine, and the ruine of the Proteſtant profeſſion? if we diſaſterouſly contend brother againſt brother, and Chriſtian againſt Chriſtian, and ſo be quaſhed by a third party. Nay ſurely, they would have long ſince executed their bloody Contrivances, and conſpiracies againſt us, had not our hands been armed with long Rapiers, but they themſelves ſcarcely with ſhort daggers. What hopes they may foſter let the world judge, if we diſſenting upon
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:116799:5"/> Circumſtantialls in matters of Religion, ſhould ſuffer the King to be <hi>Charles</hi> the Conquerour. Eſpecially when they have ſuch a nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Legatus a Latere</hi> as ſhe, who can as powerfully mediate for her Engliſh Catholikes to his Majeſtie, as the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> to Chriſt for Chriſtians, which is to pray, beſeech, and intreate, if they will not doe, compell him to performe what ſhe requeſteth. I am bold to give her a name of Dignity in the maſculine Gender, becauſe I heare that of late, it hath been a faſhion amongſt our Ladies in the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Court, to like, to love, to weare the Breeches. Small ſafety, but much more incumbrance may be divined from the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling Brethren, thoſe ſpeciall Dragooners to our State, to whom Hedges and Thickets may give advantage unawares to ſuprize us, and by unthought of Ambuſcadoes to ſupreſſe us. Who dare not op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe <hi>England</hi> but overthwartly, who dare not dare us to Battaile, nor erect a fire-Croſſe againſt us, without cheating and diſſembling pretences. Thoſe Ioabs of our daies, who will take you by the beards and kiſſe you, but ſtrike you under the fift rib with their <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Daggers, and murder you. Theſe can pretend liberty and reſtaura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of broken Covenant, when they intend an introduction of ſlavery, and Antichriſtian Prelacy. There is no device to make <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milton</hi> our friend, unleſſe we will help <hi>Hamilton</hi> to be a King; No way to make the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> invaſion fruitleſſe, unleſſe we can perſwade <hi>Hamilton</hi> to be faithleſſe; which will not be, if he depart Crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, or his miſcellaneous Regiments depart Plunderleſſe. How be we concerned to oppoſe the Chieftaines of the Northerne rabble, whoſe aymes are to be our Maſters, and perpetuall Dictators; how are we concerned to oppoſe the Excrementitious Commonalty, who are reſolved to be our perpetuall Plunderers? From irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous perſons, what hope of Religion? From ſtrangers to <hi>Engliſh</hi> Liberties, and Immunities, what hope to augment or enforce our decayed priveledges? I wonder ſober (and as I hope unbyaſſed) Judgments can expect from, or looke upon foreigners, other then as men of <hi>Galilee,</hi> from which no good can proceed. King <hi>Iames</hi> promoted the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Lords to gainefull preferments, but the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nobility (as they ſay) to name honourable, and no waies beneficiall advantages. No marvell though the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Nobles take it in great indignation to be delayed or fruſtrated of their private revenues from his Maieſty, when their greateſt ſubſiſtance was from
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:116799:5"/> him, as he bore the repute of an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Maieſtie. Their belly is both their god, king, and Equity, which if they can ſatisfie with our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Delicacies, they will forſweare fighting either for God, King, or Equitie. All is equall, if proportioned to their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites of <hi>Engliſh</hi> honours and promotions, if not, the advancement of King, Covenant, and <hi>Presbyteriall</hi> Government, muſt be as Fox-Skinnes to cover the Lions nakedneſſe. Suffer the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Lords to be Contentious for our honours, they will ſurceaſe contending a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us, dawbe up their mouthes with our fatteſt promotions, the dogges will ceaſe to barke againſt us; thruſt but an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Cruſt into the mouth of a <hi>Scottiſh</hi> dogge, well buttered, he will without clamour, or pulling by the Tarrier, retreat to his kennell. Their quarrell againſt us is, they cannot in the preſent tenſe be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted amongſt us; their quarrell againſt us is, that a Confuſion of intereſts is violently withſtood by us. There is not a better way to force our Brethren to ſound a retreat, but by a golden ſtorme<hi>:</hi> which will react the miracle of Theodoſius againſt his adverſaries, turne all the Muskets, Pikes, Swords, and Artillery againſt themſelves, rather then they ſhould damnifie ſuch loving and kinde Brethren as the Armed Sectaries, the Schiſmaticall Bands of the Independants. As the <hi>Gauls</hi> taſted the ſweetneſſe of the <hi>Italian</hi> wines, the Romans and <hi>Carthagenians</hi> of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Mines, the <hi>Saxons</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> ſo our Brethren have taſted of our Land, flowing with milke and Hony; who will never depart our Land untill they cannot depart, who will be ſupping and licking, untill an <hi>Engliſh</hi> well whetted Sword do mingle their Blood with our Daintyeſt and Princely diſhes. Greatly are we indan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered by the Cavaliers, thoſe Achillean warriours, who Laboriouſly Project not with ſword and Target only, but by commotions, lies, ſlanders, and infinite Treaſons, to murder the Hectours of our City and Kingdom, this preſent Parliament, whom if we protect, and defend, according to our ſolemn Engagements, this Troynovant of ours ſhall never be Plundered, either of Religion, Lives, or Liberties. Theſe who have been our only Saviours, and Protectors, our honourable Lords and Governors, the grand Engi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neers of our State, who have Countermined the Underminers there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, muſt now be forced (if their ſwords be not long enough) to act a Tragedie upon <hi>Tower-Hill,</hi> of whoſe executions, you are deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:116799:6"/> to be the occaſioners, to labour the cutting off the head of your Liberties, and the deſtruction of the ſoul, ſpirit, and blood of your Sounding, and Paralyticall Countrey; who, although they be infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely traduced by the ſuggeſtions of Malecontents and Incendia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, whoſe hands, although much weakened by inconſiderate friends, and Favourites, yet, how have they been before obtained, hoped for, how loved, honoured, and reſpected, when once obtained? Theſe were like <hi>Nebucadnezzars</hi> great Tree, to which all the beaſts of the field reſorted for ſhelter: Theſe were then your gourd to ſhelter your heads from the heat of Prelatical perſecutions; the ſhips out of which ye firſt durſt thunder againſt ſhip-mony<hi>:</hi> Briefly, theſe were the men on whom ſome honour is to be beſtowed, becauſe they reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cued <hi>England</hi> from the Pope, who would have made it his Aſſe<hi>:</hi> Becauſe they have freed us from the clutches of him, who would have turned a Mower, ſo you might have been the Meadow<hi>:</hi> Cut not down this Tree, leſt you be ſcattered; let not a worm ſmite this gourd, leaſt not only the Eaſtern, but all the four winds beat upon your heads; ſink not theſe ſhips with your Bullets of diſcontents, and diviſions, neither unequally Ballace them, leſt you loſe your beſt wooden wals, ſo that the Boors of the Forreſt, the falſe <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Covenanters may enter, and ſpoil the remainder of our vineyards; leſt the crafty Foxes, the Jeſuiticall party do undermine our State, and Liberties. If Parliaments be but ſauces, and Kings good meat, throw aſide theſe ſuperfluous diſhes, and you will quickly loath this Manna, unleſſe Quails be conjoyned. Though you be burdened with Impoſitions, it is that you may not be perpetually burdened. Though your tender ſtomacks riſe againſt moneth Aſſeſſements, and Exciſe, yet our wiſe Phyſicians uſe them for the preſent as an Ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to that Potion, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> muſt expell the noiſom humours out of the body Politick. Could Armies be maintained without money? or this Kingdom for the preſent defended without Armies? neither Armies would oppreſſe you with free-quarter, nor the Parliament oppreſſe you with variety of Impoſitions; but ſeeing the neceſſity and danger of the times enforce the Parliament to ſtroak their hand ungently over this Kingdom, patiently muſt we abide it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe our ſafetie is preſerved by it; wherefore, in being good and kinde to them, we are but good and kinde to our ſelves. How un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſie, and impoſſible it is for the Parliament to be ſubſervient to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very mans fancy and diſpoſition, is obvious to the meaneſt Capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:116799:6"/> and Conſiderations; to ſettle a half mortally wounded King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom ſuddenly, is to play the fooliſh Chirurgion, skin over the wound, never caring whether cured in the bottom, or no<hi>:</hi> Not to ſtay the beſt opportunity to ſettle us, is never opportunely to ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle us; not to obſerve the time when we may be conveniently Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of our Maladies doth betoken a careleſs reſolution in drying up, and curing the running Plague ſores of our Native countrey. If they would ſettle affairs of Religion, <hi>quacun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> via dato</hi> they held a Wolf by the ears; if rigid Presbyterie, the Canons would have roared from <hi>Putney</hi> and <hi>Windſor;</hi> if Independency, the <hi>Northern</hi> Bag-pipes would have ſounded an Alarm at <hi>Edenborough.</hi> To call the King home upon our own conditions, impoſſible; if upon his, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable; if upon thoſe of the 11 of <hi>December,</hi> unreaſonable. If the Militia be granted &amp; the Parl. diſſolved, it is but a diſſolved Militia before it be granted. If we muſt Treat concerning the continuance of this preſent Parli. why ſhould we Treat concerning the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the Militia? ſeeing one dying, the other will dye too<hi>: Et duo tunc morientur in uno.</hi> I durſt never confidentially repoſe my ſelf upon him, who hath once faithleſly behaved himſelf towards me<hi>:</hi> I durſt ever confidentially repoſe my ſelf upon him, who e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually in a danger was concerned with me. If Princely Oaths, Vows, and Proteſtations have proved Spiders webs, no ſafety with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Parliament, who run joynt hazards with us, upon the breaking of theſe Spiders webs. Hiſtorians have bewrayed to future Poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that Oaths and Proteſtations of Princes, have ſometimes proved like the grins which the Spider weaveth, to incircle the Hornet. The manes of the gueſts at <hi>Stockholm</hi> Banquet, the manes of <hi>Guiſe</hi> and <hi>Bourbor,</hi> perſwade non-truſting of injured Princes, unleſſe your ſafeties be fenced with ſtrong Barracadoes of Power and Authority. What groſſe madneſſe were it to ſtand Neuters, or coldly to aſſiſt the Parliament, hoping the Cavaliers brains are as often dipt in <hi>Lethe,</hi> as waſhed in <hi>Bacchus</hi> fountains; that they will commit an Amneſtye of all paſt wrongs and injuries formerly by you offered; So you will either turn abſolute Kinglings or humbly Petition the 2 Houſes for a perſonall Treaty: To expect favour and Pardon for all by-paſt injuries and diſcourteſies offered to an old friend, is a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of probability; to expect favour from a reconciled Enemy, is a matter of poſſibility<hi>:</hi> But to expect pardon from an exulcerate ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, a ſo often by you beaten, baniſhed, expulſed enemy, is a matter of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:116799:7"/> impoſſibility: who will caſt himſelf willingly into the Arms of his ſworn Adverſary, becauſe his friend hath not been ſo kinde as he either deſired, or might be reaſonably required? If the Parl. your old friends have not ſatisfied your expectations and longings, with what wiſdom do you labour a cloſe with your Enemies, offer your throats to the Poniards point? As though we could be ſufficiently revenged upon the Houſes, if we and they were burned together up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one Funerall pile.</p>
            <p>The ſame Reaſons which at firſt moved you to an Engagement with the Parliament, enforce a continuation of your reſolutions in this Engagement. The ſame party againſt you, and therefore the ſame quarrell, though wrapped up in fine linnen, painted over with the ſpecious colours of Covenant, reſcuing the kingdom from an Army of Sectaries, from free-quarter, and intollerable impoſitions. It were ſtrange a Leopard ſhould change his ſpots, or a Black-Moor his hue; that <hi>Langdale, Glemham, Goring, Lucas, Louborough,</hi> ſhould be Covenanters; that your notorious Enemies ſhould now fight under your Enſignes, and yet Proclaim open Hoſtility againſt your old friends and allies, the Lord Generall and his Army. The ſame perſons who were the Chieftains in the former Combuſtions, have anew kindled the flame, and raked up the ſparks cloſe covered in warm aſhes. Thoſe who perſwaded the King (though inclinable enough) to forſake <hi>London,</hi> and raiſe an Army under the pretence of a guard, who plundered your houſes, and burned them, ranſacked countrey Villages and Towns, raviſhed their wives and daughters, and after expoſed them to the froſty winter nights, to the mercy of the dropping clouds, and cold Northern ſtorms; who murdered the husbands and ſons of miſerable wives and parents in the ſtreets, and open fields; who daſhed out the brains of the old men in their Chambers, of the infants and ſucklings in their Cradles; all theſe I ſay, are now bandied againſt you, intending to exerciſe far greater cruelty then ever, by how much their rage, ſpite, and indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, doth boyl, and fome in a higher degree, by reaſon of the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throws and diſgraces received at your hands. The quarrell being the ſame, your friends muſt needs be the ſame; thoſe that engage their deareſt blood in oppoſition to your old Adverſaries, cannot be your enemies, the Army labour through all manner of difficulties &amp; extemities, through a ſea of their own blood, through cold, hunger and nakedneſſe to overthrow and quell your almoſt ſeaven yeares
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:116799:7"/> deadly foes and murderers. He that awards the blow of a Sword which was intended for my head, ſhall be eſteemed of me a ſpeciall friend, becauſe he performed a ſpeciall courteſie. They fight not only for their owne, but joyntly for both our ſafeties, if they would be Treacherous and revolt to the Kings party, not only Liberty of conſcience would in a large Dimenſion be granted, but the <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians</hi> eſtates would be ſhared amongſt them, as a Kingly munifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence conferred upon them, ſo Loyall, true hearted, and affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Subjects. If theſe had been disbanded, the Cavaliers would have been your Diſſeiſours, whoſe force, if you now hardly ſuſtaine, how, if the Army had been wanting to repell their violent aſſaults? if you think they were an impediment to the Kings being called home; I wonder upon what termes? ours? never a Syllable granted, his? un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable, our ſafety being herein concerned: if upon neither? How could this be effected? If not effected? How did the Army impead the Kings coming home? If their coming to <hi>London</hi> in a warlike manner were a diſturbance to the Kingdomes quiet, why was not that party in the City eſteemed as great diſturbers as the Army? who ſubſcribed great and conſiderable ſumms, choſe a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, liſted ſouldiers, prepared a new Army to deſtroy the old; wherefore a neceſſary engagement lay upon them to march to <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> to extinguiſh thoſe already raiſed Garboiles; thoſe new kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Coales of combuſtions<hi>:</hi> if any fled from the Houſes, it was their fearfulneſs, not the Armies Dreadfulneſſe which could cauſe them to foſter ſuch over ſuſpicious jealouſies. Though to ſpeake plainly, the raiſing of an Army without ſufficient authority, is an action which carryeth little leſſe then Treaſon in the forehead, then a tincture of Rebillon in its very complexion. But I could wiſh rationally to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, what the eſtate &amp; condition of our affaires would have been, if the Army had been ſhuffled off with a ſmall Pittance of money, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bentures thruſt into their hands, &amp; ſo ſent packing homewards; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would the King have inſtantly granted our Propoſitions or no? if this. The oppſition betwixt the Parliament and his Majeſtie would have continued, for whoſe releaſe the Cavaliers would have acted all their now begun deſignes, and many more againſt us, by how much greater opportunity had been offered upon their diſſolution, every one would be willing to engage in ſuch Clandeſtine Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivances, where a ſmall, or almoſt no viſible force appeared to thwart and ſtrangle their new Plotted Conſpiracies. Now that the King
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:116799:8"/> upon their disbanding would have yeilded to our Propoſitions, is meerly improbable, Conſidering the hopes he might cheriſh of a new reſurrection of his party, this army ſuffering a diſſolution; And fortune, who had for a long time drawne a curtaine betwixt her ſelf and his Majeſtie, might ſeeme now to withdraw it, and refreſh him with the ſmiles of her, for ſo many moneths Clouded Countenance. Againe, if he refuſed to ſigne the Bills in his loweſt, and halfe deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate condition at <hi>Carisbrook,</hi> would he have ſigned them in his beſt Condition at <hi>Holdenby?</hi> wherefore, the Army refuſing to disband, ſhewed both wit and fortune, ioyned with a notable diſcerning judgement; Teaching, that weake Common-wealths, for that they know not how to reſolve, never take any good reſolution, except perforce, and ſome others muſt procure their good for them, even againſt their wills.</p>
            <p>Now therefore ſhould any man well affected to the Parliaments Proceedings, behold this Army with <hi>Baſilisks</hi> eyes, be ſtoned by any of the well-affected, unleſſe it be for their good deeds, their Noble acts of Chivalry, it mounteth above the ſpheare of my Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence; wherefore, the Lieutenant Generall, who by his noble ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploits and atchievements hath mawled the Kings Party, been a Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derbag to their ſtouteſt Cohorts, and Legions, wherefore (I ſay) ſhould he be the ſubject of our obliquie, or his Honour darkened with our black aſpertions, I do not know, unleſſe the cauſe be, the fatall inconſtancy of the unpolitick and giddi-headed Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, who exalt ſome, and labour to depreſſe others, who love to day, hate to morrow, whoſe reſolutions are orbicular, their actions like wind-mill ſayles, turning upon the blaſt of ever winde, never conſtant with themſelves, and therefore cannot perſevere in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy towards others.</p>
            <p>However, I will not labour to defend all, whatſoever hath been acted by the Parliament and Army, unleſſe they were of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly race, not of the duſt of the Earth; unleſſe begot of <hi>Jupiters</hi> Braine, and not of the flowers of the field: Thus much I know, that all their errours be veniall ſinnes, and therefore excuſable, not ſins againſt the holy Ghoſt, and therefore unpardonable. But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the caſe ſtands, ſeeing ſuch infinite ſtormes and troubles doe on all hands aſſayle us, and the Billowes of raging warrs are ready to overwhelme us, wiſdome willeth, that we joyne hand in hand, live, love, and be brethren ſtill. And ſeeing all our differences are
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:116799:8"/> but about Circumſtantials, either concerning Church or State, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Policy, and Common ſafety enjoyneth us, that we do not ſo violently contend, leſt we totally exceed the litmits of Circumſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all differences; we are like two Earthen pots floating in the ſea, <hi>Si Collidimur, frangimur,</hi> like <hi>Meleager</hi> and his fatall firebrand, the one ſurviveth not the other. The Cavaliers cannot breake our Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ray, unleſſe we open ranke and file, to double diſtance. They cannot diſarme us of our rapiers, unleſſe we ſet Crablocks upon them; nor uncaſe us of our Buff-coats, unleſſe our Companions helpe to unlaſe them. If all theſe before mentioned dangers to Parliament, City, Kingdome, which threaten not only an invaſion, but an extirpation of our Religion and liberties, will not be ſufficient to incorporate our affections, and draw our ſwords one in defence of another, it is a ſad preſage our ruine is at the door, our deſtruction ſleepeth not; but in the midſt of our quarrels will throw us out of our Houſes, Lands, Religion, Liberties, and whatſoever is dearly prized and eſteemed of us. Let not the Cavaliers glozing ſpeeches bore out your eyes, to whom, if you wagg the tayle, give ſugred words, and ſawning carriage, <hi>oleum &amp; operum per didiſtis,</hi> you but carry water in a riddle, no ſafety from them to be expected, though you offered a thouſand ſacrifices on his Majeſties Altar at <hi>Carisbrooke,</hi> if before you offered up but a Wax Candle to the Parlia. ſhrine at <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Could any thing charme their bloody hands, unleſſe they were firſt waſhed with your blood; I ſhould think it no miracle, if the Lambe lay by the Lion untouched, the Sheep by the Woolfe undevour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the Gooſe by the Fox unworried; can there be continued a near union amongſt us, a neraer union will be effected betwixt a Cava<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liers neck and Tyborne. This they know, and are afraid of what they deſerve; and therefore all flie from <hi>London,</hi> and bandy themſelves to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in remote or neare adjacent Counties, fearing if they be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, ſuch Hoggs as they are like to be ſold to thoſe Butchers, whereof <hi>Gregory</hi> is one of the fraternity. And the Divell, with <hi>Machiavell,</hi> his chiefe Secretary, have dictated this project unto them, <hi>divide &amp; impera,</hi> either alienate them, and ſo ſucceſſively Conquer them, or cauſe them to ſheath their Swords in one anothers Bowels, and then <hi>Moab</hi> up to the ſpoile. If our contentions about Church Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment be laid aſide, and lulled aſleep, we may be happie if this unfortunately begotten Childe, be rocked ſo long in its cradle, untill it have taken up its lodgings in deaths pavilions; if other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:116799:9"/> it awaken, the hope is, we being all Chriſtians, and of the houſhold of Chriſt Ieſus, may friendly compoſe the occaſions of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt mens grudgings and diſaſtrous quarrellings; when the common enemy hath whipped us, we ſhall be wiſe and joyne together, dearly rewarding them for their Tyrannous behaviours, and audacions pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptions.</p>
            <p>Why ſhould we runne a whoring after a Perſonall Treaty? That new ſmoking—which the Commiſſioners of <hi>Scotland</hi> firſt voyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded out of their ingenious breeches, and now the Cavaliers of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> offer it up unto your Noſtrils as a ſacrifice of a ſweet ſmelling ſavour; As though Poyſon were wholſome Phyſicke for Naturall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, Or that any thing ſo violently proſecuted by the Cavaliers of <hi>Engl.</hi> would prove a cordiall for our differences, a remedy to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance, or a Pillar to underproppe the Tottering ſtate of our. Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Liberties. Nay, rather let us all be unanimous as formerly, if we can be but joyned into one bundle of rods, we need not to doubt but we ſhall ſoundly whip theſe lying diſſembling <hi>Scots,</hi> theſe more then falſehearted Cavaliers.</p>
            <p>The great Capt. <hi>Julius Caeſar,</hi> quieted his mutinous Countrymen with eight Letters, all making one word, <hi>Quirites.</hi> It were a ſhame for us in theſe our diſſenſions, who are all Chriſtians, not to ſtop one anothers querulous tongues and clamorous mouthes, with that of <hi>Moſes</hi> to his diſſenting <hi>Hebrews,</hi> why do we contend, ſeeing we are all Brethren? the <hi>Turks</hi> can take up a debate with a Fie! <hi>Muſſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Fie! fall out and all the Controverſie is daſhed in pieces. And ſhall not we, who are indeed the true beleevers more eaſily be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſed and joyne hands, then a Crew of execrable Mahometans and ungodly Infidels?</p>
            <p>To conclude this my earneſt exhortatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to old friends, though ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what eſtranged in affections<hi>:</hi> This know for a certaine, God is highly diſpleaſed at your quarrellings, ſeeing you give the enemies occaſion to blaſpheme the name of your God. If you will not yet be appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed one towards another but cauſe more rents and holes in the Lords Coate, God himſelf one day will ſeverely reckon with you, for that you have endangered his Church &amp; Honour It may be remove your Candleſtick, when you your ſelves have been the Occaſion, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that glorious and bright ſhining Lamp hath been extinguiſhed by the Haters of his Glory.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:116799:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
